The Bills are pretty happy with what's
left on their draft board. So, they get
right out of the first round and they're
sticking with the top of the second
round. The Bills moved on three times to
land at number 35. That's the third
overall pick in the second round.
Welcome into our NFL draft special. He's
voice of the Bills, Chris Brown. I'm
Mattie Glab. We heard a lot of people
talk about the Bills possibly moving out
of round one. Why was night one ripe for
the Bills to move out? Yeah, I think we
knew all along, Maddie, that this was a
distinct possibility. Not only because
of the lack of consensus in the bottom
half of round one in terms of players
that they deemed to be true
firstrounders, so to speak, and I don't
think they were alone. We saw six of the
last seven picks get traded at the end
of round one. I think that's an
indication of the lack of consensus, and
the Bills were part of that lack of
consensus. And I think also the meat and
potatoes of this draft, as we have said
all along, is between rounds two and
four and knowing the Bills didn't have a
pick in round two, having given up pick
60 in the DJ Moore trade, I think
Brandon Bean was bound and determined to
find a way to recoup draft capital on
day two. And he does that with these
three trades that ultimately move him
down a total of only nine spots from 26
to 35. So, in the grand scheme of
things, you only slid back nine
positions. And clearly, they have a
cluster of players on their board
somewhere between the end of round one
and the first half of round two cuz you
wouldn't be moving back nine spots
unless you felt you were going to get
players that were in that range on your
board. They clearly have a lot of them
in that area.
>> So, kudos to Bill's general manager,
Brandon Bean, for doing work in the
first round and picking up a lot of
draft capital. The Bills started out the
night with just seven draft picks. They
now have nine overall. Where does this
help Buffalo the most?
>> Well, I mean, I think it it helps in
terms of where the best value on this
draft board is. Rounds one through
seven. The best value is considered to
be between rounds two and four. They
went from one day two day two pick to
two.
>> And they went from five day three picks
to seven. And five of those seven picks
they now have on day three are in rounds
at four and five. I think more
importantly, they're also picking in the
top five. Yes.
>> In the round in rounds two, round three,
round four, and round six. They're
picking third in round two, second in
round three, first in round four, first
in round six. They're also picking
fourth in round seven for goodness sake.
So, this is a team that is routinely
picking at the bottom of the rounds
because of how well they've done in the
playoffs. Now they're in the top five in
a lot of these rounds on day two and day
three. I think Brandon Bean has done
maybe one of his best jobs at
positioning himself and the team in day
two and three of the draft.
>> Positioning positioning yourself in day
two and day three of the draft knowing
that's where the meat and potatoes
exist. Having three different fourth
round picks. Now you got your second
round pick as well. When you relate that
to the new coaching staff in this
building, to the new defensive
coordinator in Jim Leonard trying to put
together a new three four defense, how
is it helpful to have more darts to
throw at the dart board?
>> Well, not only do you have more darts,
but let's look at how round one unfolded
tonight, Maddie, because offensive
tackles and guards dominated round one.
There were seven offensive tackles and
two guards. Nine offensive linemen came
off the board. Um, only five edge
rushers came off the board. I I don't
think anybody would have guessed that. I
think they would have largely expected
it to be pretty even there. Nine O
linemen and maybe eight or nine edge
rushers. Only five come off the board.
That's an advantage for Buffalo who, as
we know, need edge rusher help. Only
five receivers came off the board in
round one. If the Bills are still mining
for one in round three, maybe round
four, there might still be some pretty
good ones left on the board. And I think
this is the most important thing,
Maddie,
and I think it's why Brandon Bean felt
comfortable moving out of the round
completely. We know they need linebacker
help. We know they need defensive tackle
help. We know they need safety help and
maybe even a cornerback for depth.
One off-the-ball linebacker came off the
board, Sunny Styles. Two corners came
off the board. Two defensive tackles
came off the board and only two safeties
came off the board. You have the third
pick in round two. You could get one of
the top three linebackers in the draft.
You could get one of the top five
corners in the draft. You can get one of
the top five defensive tackles in the
draft. You could get one of the top five
safeties in the draft. The options are
tantalizing when you're picking third on
day two.
>> Sitting at 26 and 91 to start this
night. We knew Buffalo would have a long
wait after their first round pick to
then pick at the bottom of the third
round. Now they're sitting at 35 and 66.
You have way less time that you have to
wait and you can take advantage of
drafting some of those defensive
positions if you believe this is what we
need to make our roster better. And we
know that we can find it on day two.
>> Yeah. And and not only that, you've got
three picks in round four, two picks in
round five. I don't think Brandon Bean's
done wheeling and dealing because now
you can parlay those fourth round
selections into maybe another third
rounder because as we mentioned, you're
picking third in round two, second in
round three. If you got somebody that's
falling down the board in round three
that you covet, you now have the
wherewithal and the draft capital to
make that move. You may get right back
to where you were at 91.
>> True. with some of the picks that you
you have now in rounds four and five.
So, I I just think that he Brandon Bean
has positioned the team very well to not
only get high value picks in rounds two
through four, but he also now has the
draft capital to move around the board
as he and his personnel department see
fit. Having more draft capital to do
what you want in this draft is such a
big advantage for Buffalo with the new
coaching staff coming in here to start
the 2026 season. It's interesting that
we saw so many trades happen in night
one because the weeks leading up to the
draft, the consensus was the bottom of
the first round is not as valuable as
the top of the second round will be. So,
it might be hard for teams to find a
trade partner to get out of the first
round.
>> They ended night one with trade, trade,
trade, trade, basically.
>> Yeah. Six of the last seven picks got
traded.
>> Are you surprised by that?
>> Well, I I think lack of consensus can be
deemed to be one of two things. I think
you can play both sides of the fence
there. You can argue to your to your
point what a lot of the analysts were
saying that oh it might be hard to find
a trade partner cuz there aren't a lot
of first round grades on players.
There's not a lot of consensus as to
whether there are enough first round
grades on players. But I think you could
go the other way too because when there
isn't that consensus that also means
there are teams that really like players
that maybe other teams don't like cuz
they don't fit a system or they're only
fit for this team. All you need is one
team that really likes a player and
wants to go up and get that player. And
we kind of saw that at the end of round
one. Like Chris Johnson, the corner,
like Miami uh moved up from 30 to make
sure they got him. They desperately
needed a corner. I mean, Gerard M Jam
McCoy, who was widely considered the
second best corner in the draft and
tested well off his knee injury in his
proday, is still sitting on the board
right now. He didn't even come off the
board. So, it's different strokes for
different folks. they wanted a bigger,
taller corner, they go with Chris
Johnson. Um, you there's several other
examples here. Houston trades up with
Buffalo two spots to get a guard and
Keelin Rutled is going to be a really
good player in this league, but they
traded up two spots to get a guard. So,
I think that speaks to just the
uncertainty of who likes what and what
might be one man's treasure is another
team's trash. And that might be a strong
statement, not trash, but you know what
I'm saying to go back and forth. I think
there's going to be a lot and I think
this is going to continue. I think this
is going to continue tomorrow in round
two and I really think there's going to
be a run on linebackers, defensive
tackles, and safeties. Emanuel McNeel
Warren was a player that a lot of people
projected as a first round pick. He's
still on the board. You've got Cashes
Howell, the short armed pass rusher, you
know, from Texas A&M. He's still on the
board. Jacob Rodriguez, one of the best
linebackers. CJ Allen, one of the best
line Jake Gold, Anthony Hill, these are
four of the top five linebackers.
They're still sitting there. There's
going to be a run on them and the Bills
have positioned themselves to be part of
that run no matter what position it is
because they're picking third on day
two.
>> Speaking about picking on day two, the
Bills have two picks right now, 35 and
66. What's available for them at 35,
Chris?
>> Yeah, I the linebackers that I just
mentioned, I think if they want to get
one of the best safeties in the draft,
there's a chance one of them are
available there at the top of round two.
you can get your edge rusher there if
there's somebody that fits the value
whether it's Cashes Howell Armason
Thomas I mean these are guys that are
still sitting there on the board for you
to pick from those linebackers I
mentioned and that defensive tackle
Christian Miller who some people had I
mean we've had people on our daily show
one bills live there are some people of
the opinion that Christian Miller was
the second best defensive tackle in the
draft well Peter Woods went off the
board and he was he and Caleb Banks at
18 and at 29 to Kansas City. So, you've
got Christian Miller on the board and
other defensive tackles that I think are
going to merit consideration there, you
know, uh whether it's Lee Hunter, the
Texas Tech kid. So, I think it's going
to be very heavy on defense here to
start the second round. And as we said,
the Bills have put themselves in an
enviable enviable position at 35 to
really get a quality player while
acrewing all this extra draft capital
that they can use now because now
they're picking at the top of round
three as well at pick 66.
When looking at what Buffalo has when it
comes to day two of the NFL draft, you
mention all these names that could be
available for the Bills, whether it's in
the second round or the third round,
based on players you've watched.
Do you have any favorites available for
Buffalo and who are those?
>> I would be I mean, look, I think we all
know by now I'm a little partial to
Georgia, but I I really like CJ Allen
and Christian Miller. I think those
could be impact players right away for
them. and I think they would merit
consideration at pick 35. So, I'd be
happy with either of those players, even
if you got the safety, McNeel Warren. I
mean, that's a that's a dynamic player
for your defense. There are some who
believe that CJ Gardner Johnson is going
to be more of a nickel, okay,
>> than a safety. And if that's their plan,
>> then I think safety becomes a more
prominent option and possibility. Round
three, um, you're picking at 66 now.
You're that's the second pick in round
three. I absolutely love Trayen Stokes,
the Arizona do everything defensive
back. He's played outside corner. He's
played safety. He's played nickel
corner. I know he's 25 years old, but
that's a guy that's ready to play for
you right now. Had some of the most
unbelievable tape I've ever seen for a
defensive back in a long time. I'd be
happy with him. Keonte Scott, the Miami
uh do everything DB is another guy you
could consider there. And if you don't
take a defensive tackle in round two,
you got Big Citrus there sitting in
round three, Dominique Orange from Iowa
State. These are the options the Bills
have now given themselves with all this
extra capital on day two and day three.
>> It was interesting to see that second
run on edge rusher happen. Now, it
wasn't a big run. You saw three edge
rushers go off the board. Ake Mezador
was at 22 to the Chargers. Then you saw
Malachi Lawrence from UCF go to the
Cowboys. And then later to basically end
the first round at 31, Kendrick Faulk
from Auburn goes to the Titans.
>> There's some edge rushers available for
Buffalo if they decide that's the
direction we want to go in. That was a
favorite position being mocked to
Buffalo in the first round. You still
have talent available at the top of the
third round. One player who was a
favorite name for Buffalo for mock
drafts was edge rusher Cashes Howell out
of Texas A&M. 11 and a half sacks last
season. He's got great bend, a really
quick first step, is powerful, and kind
of is a dominator out there.
>> Yeah, SEC defensive player of the year,
too, if I remember right. And you also
have Arm Mason Thomas, who's a player
that I like a lot, too. Um, I don't know
if he is a consideration at 35, but if
you trade back again because you like
everything that's sitting on the board,
maybe he comes into play if you're
sitting at 40 or 41 and you go with R.
Mason Thomas, who I think is a very
complete edge rusher because not only
can he rush the passer very effectively,
he's really good on the edge, supporting
the run and setting the edge out there,
which is saying something for a 241
pound player. Not all of these top edge
rushers are good against the run. I
believe Armason Thomas is in my
estimation, one of the more complete uh
edge rushers in the class. You got Gabe
Jacis who could be a consideration if
you slide down in round two a little bit
later in the round. And we haven't
really talked about receiver, but I
think in round three there could be some
intriguing options on the board at
receiver. Whether you're talking about
Malachi Fields from Notre Dame, um
Antonio Williams from Clemson, Deshawn
Stribbling has moved up boards, the Old
Miss kid with a lot of elite physical
traits. So I think there's options at
receiver in round three as well. The
Bills, look, I know some people just
want the high prized possession in round
one, but the Bills are picking a 26.
They saw a lot of value on their board.
Slide back nine spots, add two picks,
get a lot of draft capital to work with
on day two and day three. I really feel
like they've put themselves in a very
advantageous position to really help
their roster.
>> And look, there were several players
still available that were projected to
go on night one by plenty of NFL draft
analysts. So, it's not that they get out
of round one and there's no round one
talent available. there's still some
talent available that they could have
graded as round one talent and figure
they're still available so we're going
to get out of the first round and we're
going to pick them up in the second
round and pick up some more picks while
we're at it as you think about how night
one happened all the trades. What was
the biggest surprise in your eyes?
>> It's probably Tai Simpson right to the
Rams at 13. Um,
if you told me that the Rams took a
quarterback in round one, I don't know
that I'd be stunned because we know
that, you know, Matthew Stafford's 38
and while he's still great, you know,
and was MVP,
he's probably got two years left, like
two really good years left, um, to make
hay with the Rams. And so finding a
quarterback of the future made sense. I
thought they might have slid back lower
in the round and then he's a
consideration at 20 or maybe 21. Um 13
seemed a bit rich for me. I thought they
could have moved back and still gotten
him. And I think that's what made it
such a surprise for me. Not that they
picked a quarterback, but where they
picked him. 13 for a one-year starter
with 13 career starts. That's a big
swing. A big swing for a quarterback.
And I know he played in a similar system
there at Alabama that he will play for
the Rams. And so maybe that's what made
them feel more comfortable about him
being an answer for them. But but that
was an awfully big swing for them.
>> One thing that caught my eye from the
first round is the Jets getting three
first round picks. David Bailey, Kenyan
Sadi, Omar Cooper Jr., Aaron Glenn, and
company with the Jets, they're ready to
have a hall and show the AFC East we
want to we want to be competitive this
year.
>> Yeah. I mean, playmaker Kenyan Sadi
absolutely. Omar Cooper Jr. I mean,
they're trying to help Gino Smith as
much as they can. And then they got the
pass rusher, David Bailey, obviously at
the top of the draft. You know, in
Miami, uh, you know, moved around a
little bit, too. They get an offensive
tackle in Kaden Proctor. So, you know,
that was a good move for them. And they
get a quarterback, which they sorely
needed in Chris Johnson later on in the
round with a move up the board with San
Francisco. So, you know, they did some
things there. And then even New England
gets into the first round or further up
the board in the first round in a trade
with Buffalo and take an offensive
tackle in Caleb Lomu. I think there's a
very good chance that their offensive
tackle that started last year as a
rookie in Campbell might move inside to
guard and it might be this kid Lomu
starting at left tackle. So they might
have a rookie at left tackle for the
second year in a row. And we didn't
really think about this Maddie. This is
the second time in three years that the
Bills move out of round one.
>> True.
>> They did it in the Keon Coleman draft.
>> Yeah. It's something that I think a lot
of people had their their radar on radar
on about it is Buffalo possibly moving
out of that first round just with how
people explained this draft class and
where the meat and potatoes of this
draft class was. And the Bills do it and
they pick up more picks while they're at
it. I think it's really going to help
out the Bills and their product on the
field. The only other surprise pick I
saw in round one was Caleb Banks at 18
to Minnesota.
>> That was a little surprising.
>> Felt like a little bit of a reach. Plus
with the with the surgery concerns with
his foot, he's had three procedures on
that same foot in 18 months. He's
supposed to be ready for training camp
after getting another procedure done
just in March after the combine found
some irregularities in there. So, that's
a big risk to take at pick 18 when you
had the pick of the litter at defensive
tackle. I mean, he's an intriguing
prospect that's 66, 325, but
health concerns, I don't know if I would
have made that pick at 18. That seemed a
little rich for me.
>> It'll be interesting to see how healthy
he is for his rookie season. We also saw
two running backs go. Everybody was
saying one running back is going to be
Jeremiah Love, and you see two from
Notre Dame go. The Seahawks stick and
pick at number 32 to get their running
back because their guy, their Super Bowl
MVP, no longer with the team now Kansas
City Chiefs.
>> Yeah. And the Chiefs made a nice big
move up the board too uh earlier in the
night. Um or did they slide back?
>> They traded up to number six and they
got
>> Monsour Delane.
>> Yeah. So, they're always doing
something. They leaprogged Washington
because I think they knew that if Delane
was still on the board for Washington,
he would have gone seventh overall. So,
they jumped ahead of them and took him
at pick number six in a trade with
Cleveland.
>> The Bills decide to move back in the
first round and then they just kept
moving and moving until they were
completely out of night one. They're
happy with what's available and they're
going to pick near the top of round two.
Started the night out with seven picks,
end out with nine. General manager
Brandon Bean has Bean has got to be
happy as he's walking out the door
tonight because he knows he's got more
draft capital to work with on days two
and three. That's going to do it for us.
We appreciate you tuning in to our NFL
draft special. And don't forget to tune
in to days two and three of the NFL
draft on NFL Network ESPN and ABC. Day
two begins at 700 p. p.m. We'll see you
then.